[Music]
we often ask our viewers for suggestions
for interviewees and your name has come
up a lot I think you're probably one of
our most requested interviewees I don't
want to sort of recap too much on the
big picture of your of your books and
your theories because I think there's a
lot of that elsewhere I'd like to direct
people to the RSA animation I think it's
a really good summation of the the
general thesis it's a nice introduction
yes yes of Master Anne's emissary but
what would be the elevator pitch for
mastering as emissary it's that we are
not aware that our reality is
constructed by two different systems if
you like we focus on different aspects
of reality and therefore construe a
world with different qualities and the
first part of the book explains that in
terms of neuropsychiatry and philosophy
and the second part of the book suggests
that in the history of the West three
times we have been in a position where
to begin with a civilization flourished
when it kept both these visions together
that of the right hemisphere and that of
the left but then in every case and I
believe we're repeating the pattern for
the third time as the the civilization
overreached itself things deteriorated
and the mindset became more rigid more
bureaucratic less imaginative less
flexible less in touch with reality and
became locked into a way of thinking
which is that the left hemisphere which
is useful it's not a mistake that we
have it but it cannot be our way of
contacting reality a simple way of
putting it is it's like mistaking the
map for the territory and you you've
touched already on what the dangers are
of this what
why does do you think this happens why
do you think this is a pattern that has
repeated itself so many times well there
are a number of reasons
one is that it the left hemisphere is
really a very limited kind of organ it's
the bit that helps us grasp things it's
relatively simplistic but it does enable
you to grab things it's the part of your
brain that controls your right hand with
which we grasp things and it controls
also the aspects of our mental life
whereby we say oh I've grasped it but
unfortunately it doesn't know what it
doesn't know and it therefore neglects a
whole range of things which the right
hemisphere does know but the right
hemisphere has no speech
the right hemisphere contributes to
language but speaking for 97% of us at
any rate of us right-handers is in the
left hemisphere and so the knowledge
that the right hemisphere has is not
easily expressible and as we become more
powerful and in each case the Greeks the
Romans overreach themselves for them as
and in our case I think simply you know
the West has done the same thing again
and it's very difficult to let go of
this mentality that gives you I'll have
that I'll take that and it's very
selfish kind of way of thinking not a
communitarian way of thinking it's not a
broad picture it's a very narrow picture
it sees the short term not the long term
and it's perfectly successful in its own
terms but if what it doesn't see is its
leading into a blind alley and one of
the criticisms of your work I've seen
and I think you actually address it at
the beginning of the the RSI animation
that there was a very simplistic
understanding of right-brain left-brain
in the past maybe the 60s and 70s and a
lot of people say well that's been
discredited the whole idea of these two
parts of the brain doing different
things has been completely discredited
yes well that was one of the hurdles I
had to get
and probably if I'd had a regular career
where I had to just churn my way through
an academic career bringing out papers
every every few months I'd never had the
leisure and time and well it wasn't
leisure it was time stolen from my
clinical work but actually - I spent 20
years looking at the literature and
there's no question and it would be
absurd to suggest there's no difference
and forests are the most primitive
creatures that we know about going back
700 million years the very first ones
that have a neural network already have
an asymmetrical neural network and that
has simply become more if you'd like
more pronounced as we go up the Volusia
nary tree so the two halves of the brain
are just clearly different they're
they're better precises different
weights different shapes they have
different so-called gyro patterns that's
the convolutions
the surface of the brain they have
different preponderance --is of gray and
white matter different preponderance
--is of neurotransmitters they react
differently to hormones they're just
different and it's no good saying there
isn't the difference also
psychologically they're clearly
different because we know that the left
hemisphere for example is the one that
speaks it's the one that does certain
aspects of language and the right
hemisphere we know has other faculties
there's I spend the book explaining so
it's just that people latched on to a
very simple-minded model and that model
was that of a machine now the question
you ask of a machine is what does it do
and if you ask the question what does
the left hemisphere do and what does the
right hemisphere do the answers that
came out of pop psychology in the 70s
and 80s the left hemisphere does reason
and language and the right hemisphere
does emotion and visual spatial things
is not true they're both involved in
everything but they're involved in
different ways in reliably different
ways so it's not the watt of the brain
it's the how and that's a very important
question but it's not one that
scientists are so readily going to ask
because they're mainly interested in
Mecca
but actually it's as plain as the nose
on your face when you come to look at it
that there are these vast difference is
in the disposition of these two neural
networks towards the world they pay
attention in completely different ways
and when you pay attention to the world
you see different things in it and so if
they do that they're going to construct
two different versions of the world we
talked a lot on this channel about the
meta conversation the idea that what we
need is a conversation that opens up to
the not knowing to what needs to emerge
beyond and what it feels like is
happening now increasingly with social
media is people are getting stuck more
and more in certainty and in what they
do know is that a right-brain left-brain
phenomena well it can be looked at in
that way in that one of the features of
the left hemisphere is that it prefers
what it's already familiar with and it
finds it very difficult to shift set so
once it's stuck into something it keeps
on repeating it where's the right
hemisphere Ramachandra and BS
Ramachandran well there neuroscientists
calls it the devil's advocate because
it's able to see other things than it is
saying yes but yes but is the Zen saying
that I very much like so you can see it
that way the right hemisphere is much
more able to be flexible and also very
importantly although or not although but
just because the two hemispheres have
different takes on the world they have
different takes on their own
relationship so the left hemispheres
take is an exclusive one either this is
right or that is right and therefore
what I know excludes what you know
whereas the right hemispheres take is a
both and to take that there's a room for
what the left hemisphere does there's a
point in analysis but there's also a
point in synthesis and imagination and
what we are desperately lacking is is
that overall synthesis it seems to me
that at the moment we officially pride
ourselves on being a very free thinking
people I'm going sound like a terrible
fuddy-duddy but I think the intellectual
world was far more open in the 60s and
70s when I grew up than it is today
it's closed down to a number of dogmas
the internet which is a wonderful thing
hasn't helped because it's possible for
people to get trapped in bubbles where
they reinforce the things they believe
Without Really hearing other points of
view I'm a keen proponent that in
education and one of the most important
things one must do is teach people
always to invert everything they believe
and see the value in it in fact I
believe there should be in government a
department of inverse policy so whatever
the government is proposing there should
be a department that is dedicated to
seeing what would happen if we did the
precise opposite and it should be you
know centrally funded and I think it
would be a very useful exercise but
really it's an intellectual exercise
that we all need to do if we start being
too certain about anything it means
we've missed something else this brings
us to a very important metaphysical
point which is that a thing that its
opposite according to the left
hemisphere simply as far apart as they
can be and we move over to the linear
way to what we'd identify as good
everything I know tells me that in fact
opposites are connected and if you
pretend that you are only having one you
don't notice the dark side and this is
terribly true in psychiatry it's almost
an atchoo ism to say that a lot of the
work one does as a psychiatrist is
helping people to see that there is a
good side to what it is that they fear
and disliking themselves but there is
also a dark side to the bits that they
pride themselves on and that you cannot
get rid of the dark side you accept it
and work with moving it towards
something creative and all creativity
and all life is creative mental world is
Korea
our daily reality is created partly by
us not out of nowhere but it's grounded
in something else but we helped create
that process depends on opposition it
depends on a degree of resistance
actually and as soon as you've decided
that x y&z are good and their opposites
are bad and we must have more and more
and more and more of the thing we've
decided is good you end up reaping a
whirlwind because the things you didn't
take note of come back and bite you in
the bung and I think that what we are
now seeing in the very destructive and
and damaging and regrettable moves of
you know Breck's is and Trump and so on
entirely understandable reactions which
I like to perfectly well forgive from
people who have just been told that
their opinions are no good because these
are things we don't talk about these are
things that you know a liberal person
knows that liberty equality fraternity
is all it's about and the opposites
didn't matter so I think where we're
enduring now a backlash that we could
have avoided by having a mature
conversation yes this is good but also
forgot to take into account that this is
what we've talked about quite a lot on
the channel and our perspective is that
we're seeing the shadow of liberalism
the Trump and brexit are both the shadow
of liberalism
I didn't know that that was what you
said but it's exactly what I believed
yeah I mean you mentioned a lot of
different psychological thing because I
mean Jung's idea of the shadow is a
perfect one and it at some sense it
feels to us that this is the time of the
integration of the shadow that what
we're seeing through the democratization
of different forms of media is all the
things and the cracks between things
that we thought we've got rid of are now
rising up and I going to have to be
dealt with they're gonna have to be
integrated yes how do we do that
well of course there is no you not
expecting me to have some simple answer
and one of the difficulties is that we
have accelerated the pace of change so
fast that the kind of changes that we
require not only sort of work but simply
can
made to happen that first and we're in a
crisis which requires something to
happen very quickly really because
accelerating technological advance has
put machine guns in the hands of
toddlers we have not increased in wisdom
in fact I believe we have lost wisdom in
the West and yet we have gained enormous
Leander gaining very fast in power
inevitably if you put power in the hands
of people who have their wisdom this is
a formula for disaster and we see it in
the current environmental disaster we're
facing we see it in the destruction of
species we see it in the destruction of
the lives of indigenous people we see it
in the mind control that is already
being put into effect in China with
enormously sophisticated AI the tracks
that faces the movements they everything
the thoughts of all its citizens and we
believe I will that's China but that
could never happen here but that is very
naive democracy our kind of democracy is
fragile it's not the norm it's something
very precious and it can easily be
destroyed
especially in an atmosphere where we
don't know who or what to believe which
is becoming more and more a problem so
we have got ourselves into a very
difficult situation and I'm not
suggesting there is an easy fix to it
but there are things that we could do to
try and get away from this I mean one
that they're going to have to involve
radical changes we can't expect to go on
living the kind of lives we do with the
demands on the world that's just not
sustainable they're not sustainable even
for us and now that ten times as many
people will want to claim these rights
to extraordinary privilege the world
simply cannot sustain it so we've been
living on on fool's gold if you like so
what are the practical things that can
be done if if your diagnosis is correct
and that we're looking at a whirl
that's ever more sort of narrow and
rational how do we get out of that yes
easier said than done and and there are
patients that you cannot help which is
one of the first things you have to know
in my trade but I believe one of the
things I can do I can't do much but one
thing I can do is raise awareness and I
think that's happening so people are
becoming much more aware of in a way
I've opened people's made the things
they already knew one of the communist
things people say is I had this feeling
of southern recognition that all my life
I kind of felt all this but have no way
of articulating it so I think that that
is one thing so of course it's just a
start in terms of practical things I
mean we've got to begin by completely
rethinking education at the moment it's
about shoveling information in to people
not training them to think critically to
think imaginative Lee I was lucky in
that in my education I was taught to to
think of all sides of a question as soon
as I believed something passionately I
would be asked to defend the exact
opposite position which is a very
important exercise that I think no one
should leave school without doing you
know this is what you believe speak
about it now speak about and defend the
opposite position and we will school you
on how well you do that exercise that is
good but it's also about imagination I
mean education is drawing out faculties
within people it's not shoveling facts
into people that is the reverse of
education so I think the emphasis on you
know a cliched
[Music]
caricature would be but it's not
unfortunately that far from the truth
you're doing English a-level there are
six points you must make about Jane
Austen you know to me that is the death
of English and so is conforming it to
current preoccupations with what however
brilliant weaving they are filtering it
through isms of you know political
correctness instead of putting all that
to the site and simply opening oneself
to the incredible gift of something that
somebody created which can work on you
in all kinds of ways that you don't now
conceive the more you approach things
with preconceptions the worse it is this
is really interesting watching the
documentary you sent over hmm
you mentioned identity politics as a
left brain phenomena that it's
effectively its assert it's another
certainty or it can become another
certainty because what we're doing
through that is for example you're
taking a work of literature and you're
critiquing it not in the way that it
kind of reflects the grandeur of the
human spirit or the developmental
journey of the individual it's it's it's
about okay how does it it which
immediately diminishes it from that to
that yes and can you talk about that so
there's nothing new in there's a left
brain as a left brain phenomena I can
but I'd also first like to just gloss
through a remark because it's
interesting I didn't actually mention
identity politics anywhere in the film
but what happened you say political
correctness or was this someone else but
today what happened was and I didn't
know this that in the film as you know
Rowan Williams is interviewed and the
way the film was made was I would go and
meet somebody we would be filmed talking
together and then there was always a bit
where I went out and they just talked to
that person because then they were free
to say whatever they wanted to say and a
bit that I had never seen until the film
was completed was where Rowan Williams
chose for some reason to talk about the
angry black and white views of people
who just know what is right and wait
listen to other people and want it
legislated and he just said you you
cannot create a better society by
this kind of thing we need to develop a
society in which people can have we can
listen to one another and have
reasonable conversations and he actually
made the point that by trying to stamp
out certain things you don't diminish
the anxiety behind it you ramp it up
which is exactly what we're seeing which
is another psychological truth of
repression yes I mean that one of them
there are many problems here the one is
the left hemisphere is far too certain
that it knows what's what
it's far too clear that things are
unipolar that there are just Goods where
as you know once you see something that
is much clearer and oriental tradition
that everything has comes inevitably
with its opposite you don't think like
that anymore
it doesn't see things contextually it
doesn't see individuals it's not
prepared to listen to another point of
view it's just saying this guy I have
heard on Twitter has said something you
know which is now a soundbite you don't
hear or all the rest that went round it
you don't see this as part of somebody's
journey that it might be worth listening
to you you just dismiss it now I believe
very strongly once again that it it's
not the what it's the how if I've said
that before I'm gonna say it again and
again in life it is not the what it is
the how it's the disposition you have
now I believe it is possible to say
anything and I don't think there should
be things that nobody can say I think we
should have a system where anyone can
say anything but they must say it in a
way that is not inflammatory and that is
open to reason and discussion so that
applies to both sides of a political
argument and in that same section of the
film it made an interesting point that
anger latter eliza's to the left brain
so that so that if we're in a sort of
left brain certainty anger is the result
angrily
you know people think the left
hemisphere I mean the old view was but
he might be a bit dull but it's terribly
reliable and it's down-to-earth and it
doesn't get emotional well number one it
is not down-to-earth it's in a fantasy
world number two it is not reliable
there's good work coming out of
Gazzaniga slab sharing you know he was
the man who said the right hemisphere
has about as much intelligence as a
chimpanzee I mean that was 3040 years
ago but still his lab is now producing
wonderful data showing that the right
hemispheres far more sophisticated at
making judgments much more reliable than
left hemisphere tends to jump to
conclusions is open to bias and in terms
of emotion the left hemisphere is far
from devoid of emotion the most lateral
eyes of all emotions is anger and it
lateral Isis to the left hemisphere
naturalizers just means what it what it
means that when people are experiencing
anger there is a great increase in
activity in the left hemisphere and you
know at the chapter in verse 4 that it's
somebody called harm and James has done
a lot of research into that but the
chapter and verse will be in is in the
master sense there was a really
interesting example with birds and I
don't maybe you want to kind of explain
very simply how because that that for me
really illustrates the difference
between the two the two ways of
interacting with the world yes well well
the you know human neuroscientists were
busy dismissing it the animal scientists
were simply getting on with what society
scientist was supposed to do which was
observing and taking note and they
noticed that birds and animals use their
two hemispheres for different purposes
it's easy to observe in a bird because
in most Birds the input from the right
eye goes straight to the left hemisphere
and the input from the left eye go
straight and the right hemisphere it's
not true of human
it's more complicated but at least in
Birds and quite a lot of animals that
have eyes on the side of the head you
can tell which hemisphere is engaged by
just looking at which eye is being used
for this particular moment and what they
noticed was that birds and animals
reliably seemed to use their left
hemisphere for latching on to a small
detail like I need to pick up that piece
of seed on the background of grid and
they use their right hemisphere the left
eye for everything else for who others
are around is there a predator is my
mate nearby because I would like to
share this all that contextual
information is the right editor and the
left hemisphere is literally seeing a
tiny piece of reality now that was in
itself an aha moment I could see that
this if this was in any way true about
humans it would have colossal
implications because I have a background
in philosophy and I know that attention
changes the world so if there's a big
difference in attention one is
fragmentary piecemeal narrow the other
is broad sustained and vigilant they're
going to see two different realities and
so that got me into then looking at the
human issue and lo and behold this
difference is very marked in human being
so if people have a right hemisphere
stroke they can have this pathological
narrowing of the window of attention
like looking the wrong way down to tell
escape and you're the sort of the grand
theory as well is that we are in a world
that is concentrated more and more and
more on this narrow atomistic mechanical
way of looking at the world and
neglecting the more holistic the more
relational aspects well it seems to me
and that's the subject of a work I'm now
writing that actually we don't start
from things and then have to work out
how they relate and how this think this
billiard ball hits that one and so but
in fact that there are
very broad patterns and flows in the
world and that what we call the things
are the sort of bits that stand out to
our attention they're little nexuses if
you like that go oh I recognize that
little familiar thing that I'm gonna
call that a but actually everything is
part of a larger picture and the trouble
with focusing on detail is not only do
you miss the overall meaning the overall
purpose the overall connection the way
in which this has ramifications the bits
that are not explicit the thing that is
not in the spotlight which is everything
else but you also think that you can
understand the world by taking one thing
and putting it with another and building
it up as you'd build a Meccano set or
you know mend the bike in the garage but
the world is not like that I wrote down
from the RSA animation left abstraction
power to manipulate the already known
fixed static isolated decontextualize
explicit ultimately lifeless right
individual changing evolved
interconnected implicit incarnate living
never entirely known and that reminded
me very much of what Martin Buber
talked about but we had the I it
relationship to the ID our relationships
which I found very profound I also
studied philosophy when I was when I was
at university and that that really stuck
with me that there are two different
types of relationships we can have in
the world one the I thou is essentially
kind of on there was an unknowability
about that relationship is that
something do you think that map's on
absolutely and the results of a
reciprocity in the eigth our
relationship whereas in the I it
relationship is a unidirectional one
which is about power and inference
whereas the other one is about a reverb
responsive coming into being of
something so that is a very important
distinction and I relate the I though
and the I it to the evolution of
language we won't
time to because it's a long story but
it's in the book but in brief I believe
that language emerged from what you
might call music in other words the
music of speech the sounds and the
denotative language is a kind of special
set of a much more richly embedded
embodied connotative way of
communicating and that it became
necessary when we were no longer in
groups where you were largely just
talking I too though but we're talking
about a third party or something else we
had designs on and so that is how where
language becomes very important I've
seen your work reference in many many
different places particularly by people
who are talking about the more spiritual
the more even an author called Gary
Lachman I don't know if you're aware of
him so he he's written a series of books
about the the hidden occult history of
Western thought and he uses your work as
a way of saying as a way of kind of
maybe giving it scientific
respectability or at least explaining
this could be a process that we're going
through these these more holistic ways
of knowing have never been part of the
Western kind of mainstream tradition and
maybe that's because of the right-brain
left-brain split do you do you agree
with that well I think there is not true
that they've not been present in the
tradition I know what he's talking about
but they're very much present in
pre-socratic philosophy as we know
something very important and I think
very damaging happened to Western
philosophy with Plato and Aristotle and
particularly with Plato but these other
aspects in the West have been more
expressed in our extremely powerful
music one thing you can say about
Western civilization it in many ways is
it lacks the wisdom of Oriental
civilization but it is pretty
colossal II rich music and so it also
produced you know Shakespeare so I would
say our art is where it has been
expressed but when we start doing
philosophy we're like well we've got to
make this consistence I've see this and
I'll goes in there and this bit leads to
that and whereas you're therefore as as
I say sort of building things up from
little certainties but the first thing
is there are no certainties to start
from there intuitive you have to start
from axioms reason is based on the
intuition and it ends in intuition and
so I think there are those elements are
there but they have been sidelined and
neglected the key thing we'll must
remember about the left hemisphere is
that it's it's bright enough but not
very bright it doesn't really see that
there are things that it doesn't know
it's so hermetic its world is so
self-contained and consistent and self
referential that it doesn't feel the
need of anything else because it's not
sensing that there's something bigger
the right hemisphere sees what is
implicit what is going on not us in the
foreground but in the in the background
in the context in all these things that
are everything that we really value love
art and we used to value spiritual
truths these things are only
approachable in an indirect implicit way
as soon as you start to say well we need
to pinned us down and make it certain
you're already on the wrong track so I
think that Gary's right to point to that
it's just that I think there's more to
the story and you you talked about that
rationality begins an intuition so well
yes it has to I'm in fact it begins a
nutrition in two ways one is that we we
can't rationally prove my reason as a
helpful
we ensure that it is a useful tool but
secondly when we begin reasoning we have
to begin from quite a host of
assumptions science they officially
claims to make no assumptions in fact
makes quite a few assumptions before it
gets started it has to that's not a
criticism the system can't work without
somewhere to start because nothing could
be supported on nothing it has to be on
something before it can get started so
that's what they mean and it also ends
in intuition because the results of
reasoning have to be reintegrated into a
broader picture so it's an intermediary
tool reason and indeed the left
hemisphere is an intermediary to one way
of thinking of it is it's like this when
you learn a musical instrument you're
first attracted to a piece of music in a
broad sort of way then you start trying
to play it and you realize you have to
go over and over the fingering in bar 18
and you know there's a return to the
dominant at bar 32 or whatever it is but
then when you've done all that
that's not time wasted but when you come
to perform it if you're still thinking
like that you can't perform the
relationship with the hemispheres is a
bit like that the immediate grasp of
something that the overall take on it is
right image the left hemisphere then
gets to work and does procedural matters
but then it's the right hemisphere that
must reintegrate that information that
is not lost that process was valuable
but it must have stopped there in a
nutshell I think in our society we
stopped with the light left hemisphere
we don't allow it to be reintegrated
into a much bigger richer picture which
is in touch with all the stuff that the
left hemisphere doesn't know it doesn't
know this reminds me quite a lot of
Richard Thomas whoo yes whoo I'm afraid
I haven't read yeah no I he his book had
a huge impact to me when I was when I
was at university but but effectively he
said that he told the story of Western
philosophy and said that it had become
more and more isolating more and more a
prison of the intellect and that the way
out would
to reom brace in tuition reimbursement
get out until we did so it just it
seemed that it maps on very very clearly
to the the picture that your your
painting yes that's right
the other thing one ought to say is that
philosophy has made strides in the last
couple hundred years and i think that
there's been a redressing of that
particularly in early on in Hegel and in
the the German idealists Victor shelling
and so forth
to an extent in Nietzsche who's a mad
genius but mainly in the tradition of
two two groups one is the American
pragmatists CS purse William James and
Tom Giri and the other is the
phenomenological tradition in Europe
Heidegger
marathon T Shayla Russell to a degree so
I think in and the later Wittgenstein
would fit with that the earlier they
could Stein not you there was a comment
on the RSA video from a physicist who
said that he found it very useful in
looking at why they were so far away
from coming up with a theory of
everything because his sense was that
they're looking at the individual
details and not looking at the whole
does that make sense
it certainly does and I hadn't seen that
comment but well one of the gratifying
things has been the number of physicists
who have written to me saying there are
enormous resonances between your work
and what we are doing in physics
I thought you unskilled to recognize
those although I have an idea of the
shape they're talking about and recently
I've been trying to acquaint myself with
quantum field theory which is
actually very interesting development
out of quantum mechanics and I will try
to write a bit about that in my current
book but only after running it by some
very kind physicist friends but I think
what is important is that what I'm
saying if it is true will apply to
everything because it's about the nature
of reality and the people who are at the
coalface of reality are poets and
physicists and you know they have
written to me saying how how much they
feel the residents but what has struck
me is that people that I didn't expect
like lawyers and people in the world of
finance and economists you know are some
of my most frequent correspondence
because they say what you're describing
is exactly the problems in our realm so
I'm delighted because I never had the
slightest belief or hope that this could
happen but that what I'm saying has been
picked up by people in all walks of life
[Music]
you